<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>London's triumphant holiday being a brief relation of the chiefest memorable proceedings that hath attended His Majesty since his troubles : with a brief account of that late happy month of May's actions, in voting, proclaiming, landing, and his coming to London ... : with a short, but true account of his miraculous escape from Worcester, from that bloodthirsty tyrant Oliver Cromwell ... / written by ... Charles Hammond.</title>
            <author>Hammond, Charles, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45381</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H495</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43229</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27049676</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 27049676</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109933</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45381)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109933)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1718:37)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>London's triumphant holiday being a brief relation of the chiefest memorable proceedings that hath attended His Majesty since his troubles : with a brief account of that late happy month of May's actions, in voting, proclaiming, landing, and his coming to London ... : with a short, but true account of his miraculous escape from Worcester, from that bloodthirsty tyrant Oliver Cromwell ... / written by ... Charles Hammond.</title>
                  <author>Hammond, Charles, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Grove ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, stained, print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685.</term>
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109933:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LONDON'S Triumphant Holiday.</p>
            <p>BEING A brief Relation of the chiefeſt memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable proceedings, that hath attended his Majeſty ſince his troubles.</p>
            <p>With a brief acount of that late happy month of <hi>May</hi>'s actions, in Voting, Proclaiming, Landing, and his coming to <hi>London,</hi> to his and this Nation's Royall and faithfull Parliament; being receiv'd in great triumph.</p>
            <p>With a ſhort, but true acount of his miraculous eſcape from <hi>Worceſter,</hi> from that bloodthirſty Tyrant OLIVER CROMWELL, The Murderer of the King his Father, and the Ruiner of three Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by a Faithfull Subject and Sufferer for his Majesty</hi> CHARLS HAMMOND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Grove</hi> near the Sarazens-Head on Snow-hill without New-gate. 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:109933:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109933:2"/>
            <head>LONDON'S Triumphant Holiday.</head>
            <head type="sub">Being a brief Relation, of the chiefeſt memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Proceedings that hath attended his Majeſty ſince his Troubles.</head>
            <p>TRiumphs hath ever been allowed of, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable by all Nations under the Sun, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Heathens, but Chriſtians too; ſo far forth as we do not, in adoreing the Creature, forget the Creator, as the Herodians did. Solomon ſaith, there is a time for all things, a time to laugh as well as to weep, a time of joy as well as ſorrow. But let our rejoycing be in the Lord, who always is working for the beſt for them that fear him. This great work, or we may, miraculous wonder, May make the very Atheiſts of theſe Times ſee, there is a God that governs, that can turn and overturn in a moment; and in a month bring in a Reformation without blood, which the gods of our own inventions hath been a Reforming (De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming we may ſay) theſe twenty years, ſheading Royall and Innocent Blood to mix with their untempered morter, and with the bones of innocent Martyrs, build the walls of their confuſed Babel; and waſted this Nations Treaſure, to ſet up a bloody Traitor to Rule over it; who, whilſt he was living, (I am afraid) ſome lov'd and ſerv'd him more than God, or elſe they would not have ſo Deifi'd him on the earth ſo long after his death; but he was kept ſo long, or, as I may ſay, the Popet of him, for they took two-pence a piece in Weſtminſter to ſee him, where he lay there in his Hoſpitall Roabs, for it was beſtowed on him by the forc'd alms of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109933:3"/>Country, and they thought to have had a gathering for it; for the mony was borrowed for the preſent of ſome of his volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary or forc'd friends, which, I believe, they are all the mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that ever was for him: I believe, he did degenerate ſo from Nature, that his own wife or children could ſcarce drop a tear for him; if they did, it was more for fear of loſing their Eſtates or Honor, more than him. But what ſhould I relate more of him, it asks whole volumes to declare his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs. I ſhall, with Gods leave, here relate to you moſt of the chiefeſt paſſages, that hath hapned this laſt memorable month of May, in relation to his Majeſty, our moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soveraign, <hi>CHARLS</hi> the Second, King of England, Scotland, France, and Ireland, whom God hath moſt wonderfully brought into his own Birth-right, which hath béen detained from him by bloody Mechanick Rebells.</p>
            <p>The firſt day of this month of May, 1660. he was Voted by both Houſes of Parliament right Heir to the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, it being Tueſday, a remarkable day in this work. The eighth day following, being Tueſday, he was proclaimed with great joy and triumph in London, and the like perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in moſt parts in England, to the utmoſt of their powers, So he was proclaimed, and the Commiſſioners was with his Majeſty in Holland by the next Tueſday, being the fifteenth day, and the Wedneſday after, being the <hi>23d.</hi> day, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſet ſail for England, and Tuſeday following, being the <hi>29th.</hi> day, and his Birth-day, he was entertain'd in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, with great triumph and joy, which I ſhall for the more ſatisfaction of all you that are his faithfull Subjects, give you a brief and true acount of moſt of the Royaleſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment he received ſince his landing.</p>
            <p>Fryday the <hi>25th.</hi> his Majeſty Landed at Dover, where his Excellency General Monk fell on his knees to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, which the King would not ſuffer, but took him up, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing him more like a Father then a Subject; his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty walking with him towards his Coach, where the Mayor and Aldermen, and Mr. Reding met him; and preſents him with a very fair Bible, claſpt with gold very Rich; his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and the two Dukes; and the Duke of Buckingham, rod in the Coach, till within two or three miles of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, and then the King rid with the two Dukes, the Duke
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109933:3"/>of York on his right hand, and the Duke of Gloceſter on the left, with the General, and the Duke of Buckingham, and divers others of the Nobility being come to Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, he was preſented by the Recorder, in behalf of the City, with a very gallant Speech, and a gold Tankerd, as a Token of their loyalty, the Mayor and Aldermen being preſent; and the City did expreſſe abundance of joy. The King ſtaying there till Monday morning, where the King honoured the General with that high honour of Knight of the Garter, the King putting the George about his neck, and the two Dukes put on the Garter; none ever ſo highly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd in the ſolemniſement of that Order before, as I ever heard of; and confirms him General of England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and Ireland, and Maſter of the Horſe, and one of his Prive Councel. Divers others he knighted, as Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Robinſon, as ever a faithful Royaliſt all theſe times in London, and Major General Maſſey, who when he was Governour of Gloceſter for the Parliament, none of the King's party can ſay, but he was a gallant Enemy, and had all the Virtues of a Noble Soldier; he was valiant, faithful, and merciful, parallel'd by few of that ſide, in thoſe times of his Command; and ſince hath been a faithful Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and ſufferer for his King; an example for all faithful Subjects to imitate, to ſee the Proverb fulfil'd, after ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering comes eaſe; many more received honour from his Majeſty, and I make no doubt, but they deſerved it, or elſe ſhould not have received it. But theſe two I know, and I love to ſpeak no more then I know. But to go forward to his Majeſties march: on Monday, being the <hi>28th</hi> day, he ſet forward betimes to Rocheſter, where he came about four of the clock in the afternone, where he honoured Colonel Gibbons his houſe, he made that his Court that night, and the two Dukes with him; after he had a little refreſht him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he went to Chattam, to ſee the Ship cald the Royal Soveraign, where he was entertained by Mr. Pett, with a Banquet: ſo coming back to Rocheſter, the next morning, was preſented to him a very rich and weighty Baſon, and Ewer ſilver and gilt. About five of the clock he ſet forwards, the Roads lind with the Militia Forces of Kent, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Maids throwing the wayes with flowers and herbs, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109933:4"/>the Towns hanging out white ſheets. At Dartford Heath a Declaration was preſented to his Majeſty for the Officers of the Generals Army, declaring their joy and their faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to his Majeſty. At Black-heath there was a general Randevouz, where all the Army and all others were drawn up in order, where his Majeſty expreſſed himſelf, to the great content of all the Army. There was many bonfires there, but one great one at Black-heath, where the Maidens had got the States Arms in the Country to burn, and danſing round about the fire in white, with Muſick and a Moriſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, when his Majeſty came by, and with a loud voyce through all their Company, cryd out, God ſave the King; which made his Majeſty ſmile, a thing ſeldom ſeen, he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies being ſolid, having a majeſtick careful coutenance. So this Royal Army marched to St. George's Fields, where the Lord Mayor and Aldermen attended to receive him, and preſented the Sword to him upon his knees, which his Majeſty took and returned again. A Tent was ſet up, and a Banquet of Sweet-meats provided; his Majeſty ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a very ſmall Refreſhment, marcht on towards Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall, in this manner as followeth. The Militia Forces made a guard on both ſides, from Southwork to the Bridge, all the ſtreets ſtrowed, and the windows hung with Tape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry and Cloath, according to their ability, as rich as they could get, and many Garlands hung in the ſtreets, with the beſt Flowers; and from London-bridge to Temple-bar, on the one ſide was the Train-bands, and on the other ſide the Companies of every Hall in their Liveries; raild all the way, and hung with ſeveral Colours, according to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies Colours of Cloth. The Conduits running with wine. All the rich Streamers on one ſide of the way, with the Arms of the Companies, and the windows moſt richly hung with Silk of rich colours, and Tapeſtry, and Cloth of Aras. This was the manner of the march, firſt came Major General Brown, leading 300. ſtately Gallants, all in Cloth of Silver Dublets, ſtoutly horſt and richly acouterd. Then came 200. in Velvet Coats, led by my Lord Mainard; then another Troop, conſiſting of near 300. in Buſt-coats, ſilver lac'd ſleeves, and green Scarfs, theſe led by that loyal and faithful Subject Alderman Robinſon; then another
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109933:4"/>Troop of about 200. with Red and Silver, very richly moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, led by my Lord Mordant; after this a Troop Green, eight Footmen, ſix Trumpets, their Colours Pinck and Silver, the Footmen Green and Silver, conſiſting of about 150. another conſiſting of 250. Gray and Blew Liveries; 30. Footmen, ſilk and ſilver lace, the Colours Sky and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; led as I was told, by my Lord of Oxford; then 300. led by my Lord of Cleveland, moſt Noble Men, Knights, and Eſquires, the Coulours Blew fring'd with Gold; then 100. more Black fring'd with Gold. Then came ſeveral very rich Troops, commanded by Viſcount Harford, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of about 400. Several other commanded by Knights: the Body that came before his Majeſty, of Nobility and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, with the Citizens, and their ſervants, well mounted behind in good order, and well acouterd in habit, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Fellows I believe, conſiſting of about 3000. and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, with Trumpets ſounding, but their Muſick was drowned with the Shouts and Voyce of the People for joy; yet they were not ſatisfied with this moſt rare Show in the bravery, wiſhed them paſſed, their deſires all longing to ſee him, whom they had ſo long lookt for, his Majeſty: but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this rich Show of the Country Galantry, now comes the Citie's Pomp, in a moſt ſtately civil manner. Fiſt, came a Noyſe of Trumpets, two with the Kings Arms in their Coats, and a Kettle-drum; then the Shrief's men about fourſcore, in new red Cloaks with ſilver lace; after them about 400. Citizens of ſeveral Companies, black Velvet Coats, with gold Chains about their necks; ſome with rich Pearl Chains, of great value; every one his Page with his Livery, moſt richly mounted; after theſe came a part of the true Mourners of Zion, being Miniſters that hath been true Subjects and ſufferers, Doctor Wild, Doctor Warmſtree, and about ten more, ſuch as had indured to the end; no time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers, nor never changd their Gowns for Cloaks, theſe rid in heart (I believe) rejoycing in the Lord, to ſee the day of their Redemption here, from thoſe that would have ſtopt their mouths, if the Lord had not fruſtrated their deſigns; and thoſe Prayers that hath been counted Popery by ſome, I believe the Lord hath heard ſuch Men as theſe, that hath been term'd Baal Prieſts, by the ſons of Belial, hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109933:5"/>as Moſeſes to ſtand in the gap, and by Prayer hath ſtopt Gods Iudgments, which we fully have deſerv'd for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, Sacriledge, and Murder; after theſe came his Majeſtie's Life-gard, with Trumpet; and a Kettle-drum, commanded by my Lord Gerard, led in Diviſions by Sr. Gilber Gerard, Colonel Pragues, and two Corniſh Gentlemen, Sir Chicheſter Wreay, and Major Roſecaron; after them the City Marſhal, his Footmen in green, trim'd with Crimſon and White; then the City Waits; then the two Shriefs, and all the Aldermen in their Scarlet Gowns, their Foot-men lac'd with ſilk and gold; then came the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralds, and two rich Maces, in rich Coats, and the chief No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and Privy Councel, all riding brave; before his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty rid the Lord Mayor, bearing the Sword; the Lord General, and the Duke of Buckingham, all bare-headed; Then you might behold the three Pearls, of this Nation, his Majeſty, and the two Dukes, the Duke of York on his right hand, and the Duke of Gloceſter on the left. Three Pearls they may be rightly ſtyl'd, and I hope they will prove of ineſtimable value to theſe Nations; three ſuch Princes, no Kingdom beſides ours can parallel in the World for Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: His Majeſty endewed with ſuch Virtues, as the worſt of his enemies cannot ſay, but they are wonderful to behold, in a Prince that hath been ſo much conſtrain'd to ſee the ſuſperſtitious and follies of many ſtrange Nations, and hath never been led away by them, being much indued with piety and ſobriety, mercy and humility; as this day of Triumph you could have beheld no outward glory in habit, he riding in a plain Saſnit ſuit, his head onely adorn'd with certain Falds or Plumes of red and white Feather in his hat, the Duke of York with red and yellow, the Duke of Gloceſter was ſprinckled with ſeveral Colours, many of the Noble Mens ſervants, were in richer habit then theſe three Princes, but I believe they were counted more beautiful in the eyes of the people, then all that paſſed before, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo raviſhed with joy, ſome Ladies drapt their fans and hancerchiefs out of the windows, their ſence of ſeeing being ſo much fild, it bereſt them of all other ſences for the preſent, which made the King ſmile; he ſeeing a fan drop out of a Ladies hand in Pauls Church-yard, as ſhe was ſhaking it
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109933:5"/>about. In the Strand a many Ladies had got Rapiers in their hands, and flouriſht them out of the windows, as mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that now they would fight for him rather than loſe him now they had him. Many other paſſages which I ſaw not nor heard not, which I believe did revive his Majeſty's heart, to ſée his Subjects joy. Alſo after his Majeſty was paſſed, came my Lord of Northamton, with a gallant Party of Horſe, of all Gentry, a bout 300. or more, all richly clad and mounted; after them came thrée Regiments of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals Horſe, all arm'd cap a pe, and though they were not richly acouter'd, yet 'twas as gallant a ſight to ſée for a Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier as the other, and a better ſight in ſervice.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>That ſilver Van, flanckt with this Iron Rear,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Three Princes leads, no Nation we need fear:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Renouned George, thy Fame on earth will never dye,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For under God, thou gaveſt this Kingdom's liberty.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>His Majeſty coming to Temple-bar, all along to White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall the Militia Forces garded on both ſides, and Sr. Iohn Stowell, that great ſufferer for his Majeſty met him, with divers Officers of the Kings Army, being a gallant Party. So the King coming to White-hall, was entertaind by the Houſe of Lords and Commons, both preſented him with Spéeches by the Speakers, declaring their joy for his ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py arrival, in power and ſafety, to the thrée Kingdoms great comfort, which now they fear'd not will quickly end in peace and proſperity, to theſe almoſt-ruined Nations, for want of his preſence. The day being ended, for it was ſeven of the cloch ere his Majeſty came to White-hall; when he was ſafe, the Pieces went off ſmall and great, from the Tower, and all along the City, and not a Piece was fir'd or to be fir'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore night. Such Bonfires we made, there was never the like in England; one at the Banck-ſide ſix or ſeven ſtories high, and in Weſtminſter, was the States Arms and the Effigies of Crumwell hung up for all to behold, with torches, and at laſt burnt in the fire, with great hollowing and houp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for joy they were rid of this idol, that England had ſo much worſhipt.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now give you a ſhort but true acount, of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109933:6"/>Sufferings of this Prince before he came to his Kingdom. At his Fathers death, he was at his Siſters Court the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of Orange, whereas the news came unexpected, it came the harder; for he thought to have heard a fair end of the Treaty, and his Father ſetled: He ſtudied then which way to gain his Birth-right; many wayes he and his friends try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but all came to no effect; but the news ſtill that fil'd his ſorrowful ears, was juſt ſo as it came to Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the murdering and deſtroying of his Loyal Subjects the Scots, when they were treating with him to make him King, they thought to diſable him of his beſt friends, that they might force him to what they pleaſd to have. I leave the World to judge of their innocency, as they pretend from the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of theſe times: I pray God make their children more Loyal then the fathers, and that I hope they can take no exceptions at; pray God the ſelling of the King, and the murdering of Montroſe, be not laid to the charge of the ſouls of the chief actors of it: indeed they did what they could, ſome of them to ſettle him, and did crown him, but I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, had it not been ſelf-ends, God would have bleſt their deſigns the better at Worceſter, where his Majeſty was mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly deliverd; where his horſe was twice ſhot under him, and could ſcarce be invited to leave the Field, when 'twas ſo near loſt, the Highlanders fighting it out very nobly, but the Scotch Horſe but cowardly; his Majeſtie got away to a houſe, had his hair cut off with a knife by my Lord Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mot, then takes him to a Wood near Wolverhampton, and in a hollow Oke, and ſtaid there three dayes; afterwards brought to Miſtriſſe Lanes, by my Lord Wilmot, and by her as her Serving-man, was convai'd to Briſtol, no body but Mr. Laſted, her Father in Law knew him, where he was fain to wind up the Iack, he telling the maid he was a Naylour's ſon, which cauſd his Majeſty to ſmile, the wench gave him ſuch courſe compliments, which he was very glad to take: afterwards deſcribd by a Butler, but yet a faithful ſervant to him, and through many difficulties and dangers, at laſt got over ſea to France, where he declares his ſad misfortune, they bewailing of him, yet joyful he had ſcapt himſelf, yet this joy did not long continue in the Court of France; but this bloody Oliver never left, till he had hunted him thence,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109933:6"/>and all the Family, by making a Peace with France, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerein the Cardinal being this Traitors friend, all the time no great honour he'le gain by it now, but let him give more teſtimony, he muſt leave France; then to Holand, to his ſiſter, and ſtaid a while there; then to Germany, where the Lord ſtill raiſed Princes to his friends, and at laſt, that ever to be loved by this Nation, and that freely, the King of Spain nobly entertains him, and the Duke of York, who had been a great enemy to him when he ſerved the King of France, which will be for the ſhame of France, and honour of Spain for ever: there this wicked Oliver left not, but like the Devil, never left any means un-attempted to deſtroy him, as then he had imploy'd one Captain Maning, who was near the King, who diſcoverd all things that was done there to his Maſter here; thus the devil, and man, did work to deſtroy him and this Nation; but he had too honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a death, for it ſo inflam'd his Majeſties true ſervants, to hear of ſuch a falſe Traitor amongſt them, that he was ſhot by one of them before he enterd the Priſon: many more moſt ſtrang and wonderful tryals of patience was there in his travels and ſorrowful pilgrimages, before he attain'd to that happy Reſtoration, which God hath now bleſt him and us with; whom God ſtill preſerve, whom I hope God will by his providence, as he hath done hitherto, anſwer all the prayers of him and his friends, for him as remarkable. His Father was murderd on the 30. of Ianuary, it faling on a Tuſeday, and ever ſince he hath kept Tuſeday as a faſt, in memory thereof; beſides, it hath been known, many pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Devotions, which God hath anſwerd: it was on a Tuſeday he was voted by the two Houſes of Parliament, King, and proclaimed King on a Tuſeday, and came to White-hall on a Tuſeday; therefore it may incourage all Chriſtians to prayer, for by fervent prayer God anſwers many times by the ſame means, and the ſame time; and God you ſee hath anſwered his prayers: but how many more Faſts and prayers hath here been ſet up, and Thankſgivings, for ſhedding of blood, but what can there be expected from bloodthirſty and cruel men but hipocriſy, which their beſt Actions was no other.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:109933:7"/>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>The brighter ſtill the Sun doth ſhine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Upon a dunghill with her beams divin,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The more baſe ſents and ſtinking vapours riſe:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'le leav't to you the verſe to paraliſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Bleſſed art thou O Land, when thy King is the Son of Nobles, Eccleſ. 10.17. a leſſon very fit and obſerval for theſe times; it was taught by him whom none can deny, but he was the wealthieſt and the wiſeſt Prince and Preacher that ever was before Chriſt, or ſince Chriſt; and none but Chriſt himſelf, who was both King, Prieſt, and Prophet, had that powerful operation, and knowledge as he had; and indeed it muſt needs be for his wiſdom from above, read but Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtes and his Proverbs, and you ſhall ſee and confeſſe, that they muſt needs come from the Spirit of God though from his mouth delivered, and we ſhall find all true in them; and for this one place which I have quoted by woful experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, this our Land can witneſſe for truth, for ſince this Land hath been governed by them, who by other actions could not, &amp;c. did not ſhew that ever they were the ſons of Gentry, much leſſe of Nobility; and theſe have been the Heads and Governours of our poor diſtreſſed, and almoſt ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ined Kingdoms theſe many years, who maintaind their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives by perjury, oppreſſion, ſacrilidge, and murder; who did ſo far deoperate from being nurſing Fathers, and nurſing Mothers of Gods Church and people, who hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed that Kings and Queens ſhall be, Iſa. 49.23. they have not onely murdered their Father, that religious pious Prince, of bleſſed memory <hi>CHARLS</hi> the firſt, but they have as much as in them lay, like Vipers, eat out the Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of their Mother the Church, and not ſatisfied with that, but were about to ſacrifice her to the Idols of their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, and ſo to deſtroy her Root and Branch. Not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contented with what they had got, Kings, Queens, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Deans, and Chapters Lands, but did not ſtick to ſay openly, if they prevailed, the Church and Prieſt too ſhould ſuffer, as in deriſion they call them, which they know not that they deride Chriſt himſelf in that title, nay theſe that cry up ſo for Ieſus Chriſt, hated the office and dignity of him, who takes the title of King, Prieſt, and Prophet;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109933:7"/>and truely I believe, that they have been ſo much againſt Papiſts in their mouths, terming theſe decent Ordinances of God, that was maintaind in the Church, to be Popery, it will be proved, and is partly known, and found by ſome, that Ieſuites have been the chief ringleaders of them; for thoſe that have been ſeduced by them, I hartily deſire of God that he would make them ſee the errors of their wayes, by his wonderful works of Providence, which he hath already done in this unheard of Reformation, which he hath brough in with his Word, and not with the Sword, by the power of his Spirit, and not by the arm of fleſh, by turning the hearts of Subjects to their Soveraign, to ſubmit to him, and not to reſiſt him. God is a God of peace, ſcatter thou the people that delight in war, ſaith David, Pſal. 68. he was a man after Gods own heart, and ſurely he would not prary ſo, but that he knew God did not delight in thoſe that thirſted after blood; if David was ſtartel'd and toucht in his heart, for cutting off the lap of Saul's garment, who ſought his life, and yet he was annointed King too, ſaying, the Lord keep me from doing that thing unto my Maſter, the Lords Annointed to lay my hand upon him, 1 Sam. chap. 23. nor you never read: that he ever ſufferd his ſouldiers either to do him or his ſervants wrong, but to fly and defend themſelves. O then, with what impudence could they juſtifie that moſt horid unheard of barbariſm Murder, that was committed upon the perſon of the late King, whoſe hearts never ſtruck them for cutting off his head, a deed that they can ſhow no preſident for ſince the Creation of the World, neither by the Laws of God nor the Laws of any Land; which gilt they would have laid upon the whole Nation, ſaying, they were choſen by them; but the Lord that knows the hearts of all men, knows it was odious in the eyes of moſt of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as it is ſeen at this day; for upon the Prayers and Cryes of his Church and People, hath prevail'd, and now he is making inquiſition for the innocent blood of that Royal Martyr, and the reſt of his layall Subjects, that hath ſufferd for him. Where can they fly now from the face of an angry God; there is no way for them, but to ſubmit themſelves to the mercy of God and the King, for there is no eſcaping for them, they are ſo odious in the eyes of all, that their very
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109933:8"/>intimate Friends will not hide them, no, nor will take pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty on them; no Land-man will ſecure them, no Sea-man will convey them over Sea; if they do, no Nation will truſt them, for they that have been ſo unnatural to their own Country, and ſuch Rebels and Traytors to their own Prince, to murder him; the greateſt Tyrant in the World will hate them, and if they had acted it for him, he would ſay as Richard the third ſaid to Baneſter, when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed his Maſter, he loved the Treaſon, but he hated the Traytor; and if any Prince ſuffer them to paſſe through their Country, they muſt take it as a greater favour than they deſerve. But ſtay, my Subject tells me I am about the bleſſedneſſe of a Land, whoſe King is the Son of Nobles. O happy Land have we, whoſe King is the Son of a Noble, Pious, and Religious Prince, as ever ſway'd the Scepter ſince the Conqueſt, and this our moſt dread Soveraigne <hi>CHARLS</hi> the ſecond, whom God grant long to reign over us.</p>
            <p>I believe the worſt of his Enemies that ever heard him and ſaw him in all his baniſhment, in the worſt of times all ſay, but he deſerves the love both of God and Man, which the Lord hath ſhown by his moſt wonderful Reſtoration to his Crown and Dignity, which all his loyal Subjects did believe would be, as I believe thoſe that knows me, hath heard me ſay as much in the worſt of times, yet to be wrought ſo peaceably, ſo powerfully, and ſo ſuddenly, 'tis more then ever could be imagined, that we muſt all ſay with the Apoſtle, St. Paul in the 11. of the Romans, verſ. 33. O the deepneſſe and the riches both of the wiſdom and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, how unſearchable are his Iudgements, and his wayes paſt finding out: but Solomon ſaith, Proverbs 16.7. When a mans wayes pleaſe the Lord, he maketh his very enemies to be at peace with him; as I deſire the worſt of his enemies to conſider on, (if the Lord hath not yet recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled their hearts to him), this one place of Scripture, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring it with the actions and tranſactions of our times, we muſt confeſſe that he is our David of God, and that his wayes hath pleaſed him; for he hath made us all which were his enemies, to be at peace with him. I hope ſome may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſay, that he had thoſe here that never was enemies to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109933:8"/>him; I am afraid, if they ſeriouſly look into their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, they ſhall find, their ſins with the reſt, fil'd up the Meaſure, that made God pour out his wrath upon us, and ſo took away ſo good a Prince from us, which we were not worthy of: and I ſhall deſire all, and eſpecially thoſe that were alwaies faithful to his Father and him, and never none of times-changelings, that now the Lord hath done ſo merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully for us, that we may walk anſwerable to that mery in our converſion from all manner of wickedneſſe, that his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath been branded with, and eſpecially theſe two ſins, which they have been moſt addicted to, Oaths and Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; I believe that many have ſworn and drunk healths to him, that never either praid or fought for him; and let me tell them, whoſoever they be, I know the King's Majeſty will be ſo far from owning them to be his Friends, that he will rank them with the worſt of his Enemies. If we will be counted the Kings Party, or Caveliers, as they have cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led us, and that was the worſt they could call us, let us ſtrive to imitate him in all his Virtues, which I believe and am aſſured, by the juſt and true Reports, of thoſe that have known him, and ſeen moſt of his actions ſince the time of his Baniſhment; that they ſay, and declare, he is indued with all Virtues fit for a Prince, a cheriſher of Virtue and a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Vics; and for his mercy, let thoſe that were the worſt of his Enemies declare it; for I know no other will be look'd for from me but to commend him, who under God I deſire alwaies may command me. I will be bref with you, Frſt, You that did reckon your ſelves his friends, ſend up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as many prayers for him as you have drunk his healths on Earth to him: and in the next, Do as you would be done by, and remember that Petition in the Lords Prayer, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give us our treſpaſſes, as we forgive them that treſpaſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us; and ſeek no reveng, but remember, vengance is mine and I will repay, ſaith the Lord: and as you have profeſſed your ſelves Chriſtians, and God hath given you that faith and patience, to hold it out to the end, and now hath given you your deſire, let the World ſee, that as we hated the Hypocriſie and Tiranny, of our worſe than Egyptian Taſk-maſters, ſo we hate the thoughts of them who alwaies ſaid, oft we had had the beſt of it, how well we ſhould abide,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109933:9"/>and as they had a faith without works, let us ſhow our faith by our works, and let our fruits of the Spirit be Scripture proof with love joy and peace as well as long-ſuffering; which when we have performed that, let us perform the reſt, or elſe we ſhall ſhow our ſelves and prove our ſelves to be fathers of the falce ſpirits of theſe times, or thoſe falce lights which hath run up and down this Land, like thoſe lights that are ſeen in the night, that leads poor Travellers out of the way, till it brings them in one filthy quagmire or other, and then it leaves them; therefore as God hath kept us hitherto from following thoſe falſe lights: Let our lights ſo ſhine before men, that they ſeeing our good works may glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our Father which is in Heaven: And let us walk wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of this his great mercy, of reſtoring us our lawful King, and our Councellors as at the beginning; and I hope the Lord hath a bleſſing for this Land, in that he hath given us a King, the ſon of a King to rule over us, whom God preſerve with a long, proſperous, and peaceable reign, and bleſſe all his Councils from the higheſt to the loweſt, with wiſdom and courage, like Iethro's Magiſtrates, fearing God, dealing truly, hating covetouſneſſe: ſo ending with that Text, in the 24. of the Proverbs the 21, and 22. verſes, My ſon fear God and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change; for their calamity ſhall riſe ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, and who knoweth the ruine of them both?</p>
            <p>Thus I have ſhewed you the truth as much as in me ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, of his Majeſtyes happy arival and entertainment into London, which I am not able to expreſſe, nor is not to be ſet forth with pen in a ſmall Volum; for I believe never was any Prince in the World entertaind with more Ioy and Triumph than he was, all the way from Dover to White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall, if the inward Love of their hearts were agreeable to their expreſſions and ontward habit, I believe the World could not parallel more loyal Subjects. To them that were not ſo, I leave them to conſider the Motto of the Garter, Evil to them that evil thinks.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Convert O Lord, or elſe confound all thoſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That are thine, the King and CHARLS's foes.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <closer>Exſurgat Deus, diſſipentur inimici.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
